Preliminary Inventory to the Papers of Leonard Weinglass TAM 584
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
Leonard Weinglass Papers
1960s-2011
TAM 584
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
71.0 linear feet (72 boxes)
Leonard Irving Weinglass (1933--2011) was a U.S. criminal defense lawyer and constitutional law advocate who championed a number of liberal and radical causes. He served as co-chairman of the international committee of the National Lawyers Guild. Along with attorney William Kunstler, Weinglass represented the Chicago 7 in their 1968 trial. He also participated in the defense of Daniel Ellsberg and Anthony Russo, who were charged with leaking the Pentagon Papers and whose trial ended in a dismissal of all charges. In 1970, he represented and won the acquittal of Angela Davis who was charged with participation in the abduction and murder of a local judge. Weinglass was the lead defense attorney for Mumia Abu-Jamal for several years. In 1995, he authored a book about Abu-Jamal's case entitled Race for Justice: Mumia Abu Jamal's Fight Against the Death Penalty. The unprocessed Leonard Weinglass Papers contain case files and related material for many famous legal struggles, such as the Pentagon Papers, Mumia Abu-Jamal, and the Chicago Seven, as well as other cases, including those of Kurt Alan Stand and Susan Komarisuk. Weinglass's speaking engagements (including re the case of Daniel Ellsberg) and research files also make up a significant part of the collection. Aside from paper records, the collection contains audio-visual materials and artwork.
Weinglass, Leonard
Historical/Biographical Note
Leonard Irving Weinglass (August 27, 1933--March 23, 2011) graduated from Yale Law School in 1958 and was a U.S. criminal defense lawyer and constitutional law advocate who championed a number of liberal and radical causes. An expert in constitutional law, he served as co-chairman of the international committee of the National Lawyers Guild. Along with attorney William Kunstler, Weinglass represented the Chicago 7 in their 1968 trial. He also participated in the defense of Daniel Ellsberg and Anthony Russo, who were charged with leaking the Pentagon Papers and whose trial ended in a dismissal of all charges. In 1970, he represented and won the acquittal of Angela Davis who was charged with participation in the abduction and murder of a local judge. Weinglass was the lead defense attorney for Mumia Abu-Jamal for several years. In 1995, he authored a book about Abu-Jamal's case entitled Race for Justice: Mumia Abu Jamal's Fight Against the Death Penalty.
Other prominent clients included Kathy Boudin, a member of the Weather Underground charged with felony murder for her participation in an armed robbery; anti-war activist Ron Kaufman; Bill and Emily Harris (of the SLA) and Jimi Simmons, among others. In 1972, Weinglass took on the defense of John Sinclair, Chairman of the White Panther Party in Detroit, Michigan. The case became United States v. U.S. District Court, 407 U.S. 297 (1972) on appeal to the United States Supreme Court, a landmark decision prohibiting the government's use of electronic surveillance without a warrant. In 1985, Weinglass successfully defended Stephen Bingham, an attorney accused of smuggling a handgun to George Jackson in San Quentin Prison setting off an escape attempt that resulted in the death of Jackson, two other inmates, and three prison guards. Weinglass was the lead appellate attorney for the Cuban Five from 2002 until his death in 2011.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions. NOTE: The collection is stored offsite and advance notice is required for use.
Scope and Contents note
The unprocessed Leonard Weinglass Papers contain case files and related material for many famous legal struggles, such as the Pentagon Papers, Mumia Abu-Jamal, and the Chicago Seven, as well as other cases, including those of Kurt Alan Stand and Susan Komarisuk. Weinglass's speaking engagements (including re the case of Daniel Ellsberg) and research files also make up a significant part of the collection. Aside from paper records, the collection contains audio-visual materials and artwork.
Abu-Jamal, Mumia; Davis, Angela Y. (Angela Yvonne), 1944-; Ellsberg, Daniel.; Komisaruk, Susan Alexis; National Lawyers Guild.; Smith, Michael Steven, 1942-; Stand, Kurt Alan; Weinglass, Leonard; Chicago Seven Trial, Chicago, Ill., 1969-1970; Civil rights |z United States.; Constitutional law |z United States |v Cases.; Freedom of information |x Government policy |z United States.; Lawyers |x Political activity |z United States.; Legal correspondence.; Legal documents.; Legal files.; Research (document genres).; Speeches.; Trials (Political crimes and offenses) |z United States.
- Inventory
  - Files on Individuals (correspondence, clippings, etc.) and Contempt of Court Decision (1995), 1990s-2000s (Box 1)
  - Novaspes Records (including board minutes), 1996-2001 (Box 2)
  - U.S. v. Susan Alexis Komisaruk, 1987-1989 (Box 3)
  - Research Files for Article on Contempt of Court, 1970s-1990s (Box 4)
  - Files on Individuals (correspondence, clippings, etc.) and Organizations (especially anti-death penalty groups), 1990s-2000s (Box 5)
  - U.S. v. Filiberto Ojeda Rios, et al, 1989-1990 (Box 6)
  - Speaking Materials Research: Crime, Prisons, Law, and Government, 1970s-2000s (Box 7)
  - Travel, 2006-2007 (Box 8)
  - U.S. v. Susan Alexis Komisaruk, 1987-1989 (Box 9)
  - Research Files on Juries, 1960s-1970s (Box 10)
  - Film and Video of "Chicago Seven" (Pacific Street Films), undated (Box 11)
  - 4 West 21st Street (NYC) Construction (2005), Diane Downey/Daniel Ligget Case, Jacques Loussier v. Universal Music Group ("Eminem Case"), William Guerrero, et al v. Jerome Terrace, et al ("Feldman Case"), and Craig Winchell Parole, 1970-2005 (Box 12)
  - Files on Individuals (correspondence, clippings, etc.) and Real Estate Records, 1983-2009 (Box 13)
  - Alliance for Global Justice, et al v. District of Columbia, et al; Discovery: FBI Files on Anti-World Bank and International Monetary Fund (IMF) Protests, 2000-2010 (Box 14)
  - Death Penalty, 1970s-2000s (Box 15)
  - International Law, the Necessity Defense, Peru Case, Criminal Law Reporter, and Student Papers, 1980s-2000s (Box 16)
  - Research Files on Juries and Student Papers, 1970s (Box 17)
  - Research Files on Juries, Student Papers, and Various Cases Ordered by Subject, 1970s-2003 (Box 18)
  - Prisoners' Correspondence, Human Trafficking, and Various Manuscripts and Court Transcripts, 1970s-2008 (Box 19)
  - FBI Files on Weinglass, Speaking Materials, and California v. William Taylor Harris and Emily Montague Harris, 1970s-2000s (Box 20)
  - U.S. v. Alexander Sanchez, U.S. v. Gerardo Hernandez, et al, and General Legal Files, 1990s-2000s (Box 21)
  - Newark Water Case, Melissa Roxas Case (Philippines), Mammilla Cemetery Case (Jerusalem), New York v. Everton McKenzie, and Other Recent Cases, late 2000s (Box 22)
  - U.S. v. Kurt Alan Stand and Files on Courtroom Techniques, 1970s-late 1990s (Box 23)
  - California v. Angela Y. Davis and Ruchell Magee, U.S. v. Anthony Joseph Russo and Daniel Ellsberg, U.S. v. Victor Gerena, et al, Judicial Misconduct, and Iran-Contra, early 1970s-late 1980s (Box 24)
  - U.S. v. Anthony Joseph Russo and Daniel Ellsberg, U.S. v. Ronald Kaufman, and Flag Burning, 1970s-1980s (Box 25)
  - Subject Files: U.S. Presidents, Rights of the Accused, Punishment/Prisons, Civil Liberties, U.S. War Crimes, Prosecutors, Israel, Federal Courts/Supreme Courts, Law Enforcement, the Rich, Poverty, the Economy, Race, the Military, and Cuba, 2000s (Box 26)
  - Jury Nullification and the Necessity Defense, 1970s-1980s (Box 27)
  - Speaking Files (including text of speeches), 1970-2011 (Box 28)
  - Speaking Files: Supportive Materials (includes files on human rights, torture, incarceration, and the Patriot Act) [folder level inventory inside box), 1990s-2000s (Box 29)
  - Speaking Files: Supportive Materials (includes files on foreign affairs, Israel, and various "personalities") [folder level inventory inside box), 1990s-2000s (Box 30)
  - Chicago Conspiracy Trial, Conference on Cuba, and Ongoing Cases, 1970s-late 2000s (Box 31)
  - Center for Human Rights and Constitutional Law v. National Geospatial-Intelligence Agency, National Aeronautics and Space Administration and Other Recent Cases, 1970s-2011 (Box 32)
  - Legal Research on Juries, 1970s-1980s (Box 33)
  - U.S. v. Victor Gerena, et al, 1980s (Box 34)
  - Mumia Abu-Jamal Publicity, 1990s (Box 35)
  - Class Action Lawsuit vs. International Medical Research and Novaspes (including settlement and bankruptcy), 2000s (Box 36)
  - Mumia Abu-Jamal, Sam Rosenwein Oral History, Dave Dellinger, Bloom v. Cochran, Wang Wu Case, Daniel Gross Case (includes video), Gerry Civin v. Reads Associates, et al, and Several Unlabeled Videos, 1989-early 2000s (Box 37)
  - Speaking Materials, U.S. v. Anthony Joseph Russo and Daniel Ellsberg, and California v. William Taylor Harris and Emily Montague Harris, 1960s-1970s (Box 38)
  - "Finished Cases, 2000-2001" (folder inventory on top of the box) and Bruderhof Material relating to Mumia Abu-Jamal, late 1990s-early 2000s (Box 39)
  - U.S. v. Victor Manuel Gerena, et al, 1980s (Box 40)
  - Correspondence and Meetings with Mumia Abu-Jamal, Family Correspondence and Writings, and Kathy Boudin, 1960s-1990s (Box 41)
  - Khader Musa Hamide and Michel Ibrahim Shehadeh Case, Palestine, U.S. v. Ruben Campa, et al, and Class Action Lawsuit vs. International Medical Research and Novaspes, 1990s-2004 (Box 42)
  - U.S. v. Ruben Campa, et al and Class Action Lawsuit vs. International Medical Research and Novaspes, 1990s-early 2000s (Box 43)
  - Videos (mostly regarding Mumia Abu-Jamal) and Audio Cassettes (mostly speeches and lectures by Weinglass and others), circa 1980s-1990s (Box 44)
  - Posters, Photographs, and Framed Artwork (Box 45)
  - Phonograph Record of Chicago Conspiracy Trial Play, Posters, Photographs, and Framed Artwork (Box 46)
  - Oversized Framed Work of Art (in need of custom box)
  - VHS Tapes and DVDs (mostly of Weinglass Speeches), Air Force Records, and Miscellaneous Recent Files, 1970, 1990s-2010 (Box 47)
  - General Files, 1980s-2010 (Box 48)
  - Speaking Files, 2000s (Box 49)
  - Chicago Trial and Related Material, 1960s (Box 50)
  - U.S. v. Anthony Joseph Russo and Daniel Ellsberg, 1960s-1970s (Box 51)
  - U.S. v. Kurt Alan Stand, late 1990s-2000s (Box 52)
  - U.S. v. Kurt Alan Stand, late 1990s-2000s (Box 53)
  - U.S. v. Kurt Alan Stand, late 1990s-2000s (Box 54)
  - U.S. v. Kurt Alan Stand, late 1990s-2000s (Box 55)
  - U.S. v. Kurt Alan Stand, late 1990s-2000s (Box 56)
  - U.S. v. Ahmed Omar Abu Ali [Folder level inventory inside box], 2000s (Box 57)
  - U.S. v. Ahmed Omar Abu Ali [Folder level inventory inside previous box], 2000s (Box 58)
  - Association of Professional Flight Attendants, 2000s (Box 59)
  - Association of Professional Flight Attendants, 2000s (Box 60)
  - Association of Professional Flight Attendants and Cooper, et al. v. TWA Airlines, et al. (includes CD-ROM), 2000s (Box 61)
  - LA 8, 1980s-1990s (Box 62)
  - LA 8, 1980s-1990s (Box 63)
  - U.S. v. Kurt Alan Stand, late 1990s-2000s (Box 64)
  - U.S. v. Kurt Alan Stand, late 1990s-2000s (Box 65)
  - Speaking Files: Supportive Materials, 1970s-1980s (Box 66)
  - Class Action Lawsuit vs. International Medical Research and Novaspes, 1990s-2000s (Box 67)
  - Harvey/Klein and Texfel, 1990s-2000s (Box 68)
  - Teaching Materials (primarily USC Criminal Trial Advocacy class); Notes re: Pentagon Papers Case; Loose Pages Involving Various Cases, 1969-1982 (Box 69)
  - USA v. Anthony Joseph Russo, et al.; select portions of lega texts on topics such as Cross Examination, Closing Argument, 1972-1975 (Box 70)
  - Personal: Speeches, Memorabilia, Photographs, Publicity, Travel, Material re: Mumia Abu-Jamal, Phil Berrigan, Alger Hiss and others, 1970-2000 (Box 71)
  - Personal: Speaking Engagements, Photographs, Memorabilia, Publicity, Travel, Speaking Materials, 1976-1999 (Box 72)